1 Introduction
In this coursework you will build a distributed storage system. This will involve knowledge of Java, networking and distributed systems. The system has one Controller and N Data Stores (Dstores). It supports multiple concurrent clients sending store, load, list, remove requests. You will implement Controller and Dstores; the client will be provided. Each file is replicated R times over different Dstores. Files are stored by the Dstores, the Controller orchestrates client requests and maintains an index with the allocation of files to Dstores, as well as the size in byte of each stored file. The client actually gets the files directly from Dstores – which improves scalability. For simplicity, all these processes will be on the same machine, but the principles are similar to a system distributed over several servers. Files in the distributed storage are not organised in folders and sub- folders. Filenames do not contain spaces.
The Controller is started first, with R as an argument. It waits for Dstores to join the storage system (see Rebalance operation). The Controller does not serve any client request until at least R Dstores have joined the system.
As Dstores may fail and new Dstores can join the storage system at runtime, rebalance operations are required to make sure each file is replicated R times and files are distributed evenly over the Dstores.

2 Networking
Controller, Dstores and Clients will communicate with each other via TCP connections. Because they will be on the same machine, the Dstores will listen on different ports.
Each client will submit requests to the Controller sequentially over a separate TCP connection.
The Dstores will establish connections with the Controller as soon as they start. These connections will be persistent (i.e., they are expected to be kept alive for as long as the Dstore is running). All the communications between a Dstore and the Controller must take place over that connection; no further connections must be established between a Dstore and the Controller. If the Controller detects that the connection with one of the Dstores dropped, then such a Dstore will be removed from the set of Dstores that are part of the storage system. If a Dstore detects that the connection with the Controller dropped, it should not try to establish a new connection with the Controller.
Processes should send textual messages (e.g., LIST – see below) using the println() method of PrintWriter class, and receive using the readLine() method of BufferedReader class. For data messages (i.e., file content), processes should send using the write() method of OutputStream class and receive using the readNBytes() method of InputStream class.


3 The Index
The index refers to the data structure used by the Controller to keep track of stored files. As Store and Remove operations involve a number of messages to be completed (see Section 4), it is important to ensure that other possibly conflicting concurrent operations are served properly. To achieve that, the index data structure should include a dedicated field for each file to record its current state.
For example, while a file F is being stored (i.e., corresponding index entry updated with state set to “store in progress”), we do not want the storage system to serve any Load or Remove operations on F, nor to include F when List operations are invoked. In this sense, it should be as if F does not exist yet. However, if another concurrent Store operation is requested for another file with the same name of F, then we want to reply with an ERROR ALREADY_EXISTS message. Handling this kind of situations requires to explicitly manage the lifecycle of files, e.g., from "store in progress" to "store complete" to "remove in progress" to "remove complete". When a file is in the "remove complete" state, it can be removed from the index. The expected behaviour of the storage system in these situations is defined at the end of Section 4.

4 Code development
You can use the latest version of Java openjdk-21-jdk, on Linux/Unix. Do not use Windows. The code must be testable and not depend on any IDE directory structure/config files.
Command line parameters to start up the system:
Controller:	java Controller cport R timeout rebalance_period
A Dstore:	java Dstore port cport timeout file_folder
A client:	java Client cport timeout

The Controller is given a port to listen on (cport), a replication factor (R), a timeout in milliseconds (timeout) and how long to wait (in seconds) to start the next rebalance operation (rebalance_period).
A Dstore is started with the port to listen on (port) and the controller’s port to talk to (cport), timeout in milliseconds (timeout) and where to store the data locally (file_folder). Each Dstore should use a different path and port, so they don’t clash. The client is started with the controller port to communicate with it (cport) and a timeout in milliseconds (timeout).

Controller and Dstores do not need to keep any state between different executions. This means the Controller does not need to save/load the index to/from disk, and Dstores must empty their file folder at start up. You can assume the folder already exists; it does not need to be created by the Dstore.

The timeout should be used when a process expects a response from another process; for example, when the Controller waits for a Dstore to send a STORE_ACK message (see below Store operation). Timeouts should not be used in other circumstances; for example, when the Controller waits for a Client to send a request.


Join operation
This operation is started by a Dstore that wants to join the storage system.
• Dstore → Controller: JOIN port
Where port is the endpoint of the new Dstore.

Store operation
• Client → Controller: STORE filename filesize
• Controller
o Updates index, “store in progress”
o Selects R Dstores, their endpoints are port1, port2, …, portR
o Ensure files are distributed evenly among Dstores1
o Controller → Client: STORE_TO port1 port2 … portR
• For each Dstore i
o Client → Dstore i: STORE filename filesize
o Dstore i → Client: ACK
o Client → Dstore i: file_content
o Once Dstore i finishes storing the file,
Dstore i → Controller: STORE_ACK filename
• Once Controller received all acks
o updates index, “store complete”
o Controller → Client: STORE_COMPLETE

Dstores might be terminated during this operation. You can assume all files are not empty (i.e., file size is always greater than zero) and their size is lower than 100KB. All filesize values are in bytes.

Failure Handling 
• Malformed message received by Controller/Client/Dstore
o Ignore message (it would be good practice to log it)
• If not enough Dstores have joined
o Controller → Client: ERROR_NOT_ENOUGH_DSTORES
• If filename already exists in the index
o Controller → Client: ERROR_FILE_ALREADY_EXISTS
• If the Controller does not receive all the acks (e.g., because the timeout expires), the STORE_COMPLETE message should not be sent to the Client, and filename should be removed from the index.
















1 With N Dstores, replication factor R, and F files, each Dstore should store between floor(RF/N) and ceil(RF/N) files, inclusive

Load operation
• Client → Controller: LOAD filename
• Controller selects one the R Dstores that stores that file, let port be its endpoint
• Controller → Client: LOAD_FROM port filesize
• Client → Dstore: LOAD_DATA filename
• Dstore → Client: file_content
All filesize values are in bytes. Dstores might be terminated during this operation. Failure Handling 
• Malformed message received by Controller/Client/Dstore
• Ignore message (it would be good practice to log it)
• If not enough Dstores have joined
o Controller → Client: ERROR_NOT_ENOUGH_DSTORES
• If file does not exist in the index
o Controller → Client: ERROR_FILE_DOES_NOT_EXIST
• If Client cannot connect to or receive data from Dstore
o Client → Controller: RELOAD filename
o Controller selects a different Dstore with endpoint port’
• This requires the Controller to keep track of which ports have been selected for the last LOAD/RELOAD operation of each active Client; this information can be reset once the Client sends another request that is not a RELOAD
o Controller → Client: LOAD_FROM port’ filesize
• All filesize values are in bytes
o If Client cannot connect to or receive data from any of the R Dstores
• Controller → Client: ERROR_LOAD
• If Dstore does not have the requested file
o Simply close the socket with the Client

Remove operation
• Client → Controller: REMOVE filename
• Controller updates index, “remove in progress”
• For each Dstore i storing filename
o Controller → Dstore i: REMOVE filename
o Once Dstore i finishes removing the file,
Dstore i → Controller: REMOVE_ACK filename
• Once Controller received all acks
o Remove filename from the index
o Controller → Client: REMOVE_COMPLETE
Dstores might be terminated during this operation. Failure Handling 
• Malformed message received by Controller/Client/Dstore
o Ignore message (it would be good practice to log it)
• If not enough Dstores have joined
o Controller → Client: ERROR_NOT_ENOUGH_DSTORES
• If filename does not exist in the index
o Controller → Client: ERROR_FILE_DOES_NOT_EXIST
• Controller cannot connect to some Dstore, or does not receive all the ACKs within the timeout
o No further action, the state of the file in the index will remain "remove in progress"; future rebalances will try to sort things out by ensuring that no Dstore stores that file
o The timer to detect timeouts should start right after the Controller has sent the REMOVE message to all Dstores
• If Dstore does not have the requested file
o Dstore → Controller: ERROR_FILE_DOES_NOT_EXIST filename
o In this case, the Controller can handle this message as if it were a REMOVE_ACK because in either that Dstore is no longer storing filename

List operation
• Client → Controller: LIST
• Controller → Client: LIST file_list
o file_list is a space-separated list of filenames

Dstores might be terminated during this operation. The controller must only include in the list returned those files that are in "store complete" status. If there are no files to return, the Controller should reply LIST.

Failure Handling 
• Malformed message received by Controller/Client
o Ignore message (it would be good practice to log it)
• If not enough Dstores have joined
o Controller → Client: ERROR_NOT_ENOUGH_DSTORES

	
Concurrent Operations
• Ongoing operation: Store file
o If a concurrent Store operation on the same file is received, then return ERROR_FILE_ALREADY_EXISTS
o If a concurrent Load operation on the same file is received, then return ERROR_FILE_DOES_NOT_EXIST
o If a concurrent Remove operation on the same file is received, then return ERROR_FILE_DOES_NOT_EXIST
o If a concurrent List operation is received, then do not include file in the list to return
• Ongoing operations: Remove file
o If a concurrent Store operation on the same file is received, then return ERROR_FILE_ALREADY_EXISTS
o If a concurrent Load operation on the same file is received, then return ERROR_FILE_DOES_NOT_EXIST
o If a concurrent Remove operation on the same file is received, then return ERROR_FILE_DOES_NOT_EXIST
o If a concurrent List operation is received, the do not include file in the list to return

5 Submission Requirements
• Your submission should include the following files:
o Controller.java
o Dstore.java
As well as all the additional .java files you developed
• These files should be contained in a single zip file called <your username>.zip
• There should be no package structure to your java code
• When extracted from the zip file, the files should be located in the current directory
• These files will be executed at the Linux command line by us for automatic testing

6 Marking Scheme
You are asked to implement the Controller and Dstores. You will be given the client, as an obfuscated jar. The client allows the execution of operations via a terminal.

• Up to 50 marks are awarded based on whether the storage system works in compliance with the protocol when serving sequential requests from a single client
• Up to 10 marks are awarded based on whether each file is evenly replicated R times across the Dstores (only when stored, not when Dstores fail or new Dstores join the storage system)
• Up to 10 marks are awarded based on whether the storage system correctly serves concurrent requests from more clients (up to 10 concurrent clients)
• Up to 10 marks are awarded based on whether the storage system correctly tolerates the failure of one Dstore
• Up to 10 marks are awarded based on whether the storage system correctly tolerates the failure of up to N-R Dstores
• Up to 10 marks are awarded based on whether files are evenly spread over the Dstores despite Dstores failing or joining the storage system

7 Code development suggestions
There are various things to develop step-by-step. This includes making TCP connections and passing data to/from, implementing timeouts for when the communication is broken, and so on. This is a good place to start.
• Draw an outline of your system to keep track of the functionality/code structure
• Use techniques you tested from the Java sockets worksheet.
• For the Controller, you can start by making it accept connections
• Avoid multithreading until you are ready for it
• Make sure your Controller and Dstores print detailed log messages to stdout/stderr
• Work with just the Dstore to be able to save and read files
• Progressively add the features such as delete and allocating files to Dstores
• Test progressively so you know each area works and can return errors.
• Finally write the rebalance operations


8 Objectives
This coursework has the following module aims, objectives and learning outcomes: A5. Client-server applications and programming
D1. Build a client-server solution in Java
D2. Build a distributed objects solution in Java D3. Build and operate simple data networks
B5. Understand the use and impact of concurrency on the design of distributed systems


